Guide to the J. M. Barrie Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1876–1954; Series II; 16.5; 35 boxes
  - Other Writings
    - The Allahakbarrie Book of Broadway Cricket for 1899 (Box 50, Folder 1051)
      Autograph manuscript, with author's corrections and markings for the printer. Inscribed to Charles P. Johnson, January 24, 1918, and bound with Barrie's autograph letter, signed, to Johnson, dated January 25, 1918. Accompanied by printed version.
    - "Andrew Lang Plagiarist", 1890 (Box 50, Folder 1052)
      Autograph manuscript, signed. Published under heading "Mr. Plagiary Lang" and signed by "A Woman of Letters" in the Correspondence section of the Scots Observer, June 14, 1890. Bound with the manuscript is a Foreword by an unidentified person, a typed copy of the text of the article, and a typed copy of a reply to the Barrie article as published in the Scots Observer, June 28, 1890. Bound in green morocco.
    - "Aucassin and Nicolette", undated (Box 50, Folder 1053)
      Autograph manuscript, signed, with markings for the printer.
    - "The Autobiography of a Joke", circa 1896 (Box 50, Folder 1054)
      Typed copy of an article supposedly by Barrie.
      Gift of Mary Hyde Eccles, 1979.
    - "Bad Form" or "An Inconsiderate Waiter", undated (Box 51, Folder 1055)
      Autograph manuscript, signed, with autograph corrections and additions, of an account of various waiters at the club to which Barrie had belonged for thirty years. Published as "The Inconsiderate Waiter" in the Christmas number of the Illustrated London News (1891). Bound in yellow morocco.
    - "Barrie at Bay: which was Brown?"
      - Autograph manuscript, 1914 (Box 51, Folder 1056)
        Hypothetical interview between a reporter and Barrie's valet, Brown, published anonymously in the New York Times, October 1, 1914. Bound with the manuscript are a typed note, signed by Thomas Lennox Gilmour, explaining the origin of the "interview," a copy of the "interview" as published in the New York Times, and an autograph manuscript letter from Vilhjalmur Stefansson to the author, dated October 24, 1916. Bound in full brown morocco.
      - Two typescripts of Gilmour's explanation of the interview, 1914 (Box 51, Folder 1057)
    - "The Boy with Two Mothers", [1885-1887] (Box 51, Folder 1058)
      Autograph manuscript article, signed.
    - "Candidates on the Rack", [1886?] (Box 51, Folder 1059)
    - "Charles Frohman", [1915] (Box 51, Folder 1060)
      Autograph manuscript, signed, of a tribute to the American impresario Charles Frohman published in the Daily Mail, London, May 10, 1915. Accompanied by an autograph letter, signed, to James Waters, the drama critic to the Daily Mail, dated May 9, 1915, regarding publication details.
    - "Chess", [1920] (Box 51, Folder 1061)
      Autograph manuscript notes and draft for an article on chess.
    - "The China of Tomorrow", [1886] (Box 51, Folder 1062)
    - "The Comic Bible", [1883-1887] (Box 51, Folder 1063)
      Autograph manuscript article, signed. This manuscript bears the London address which Barrie used from 1885-1887; an article with the same title was published in the Nottingham Journal, December 17, 1883. Another version of this article can be found in Notebook 3 (Box 21).
    - "A Confession", 1903 (Box 51, Folder 1064)
      Autograph manuscript, signed, with autograph deletions, revisions, and additions. See letter to H. B. Baildon in Series I.
    - Continuation of account of rehearsal on roof of Wyndham's Theatre, undated (Box 51, Folder 1065)
      Autograph manuscript of a fictitious interview with Irene Vanbrugh. There are two extra leaves numbered 7½ and 9½. Accompanied by an envelope with a note in the hand of Lady Cynthia Asquith: "Original article written by J. M. Barrie May 27—never published."
    - "Engagement: putting it to her", [1884-1885] (Box 51, Folder 1066)
      Autograph manuscript notes for a story in the "Auld Licht" manner.
    - "First Bite at a Cherry", [1891?] (Box 51, Folder 1067)
      Autograph manuscript of an article concerning the production of Barrie's play, Ibsen's Ghost. Irene Vanbrugh, J. L. Toole, and Sir Henry Irving are the principal characters.
    - "Four Books a Year", [1889] (Box 51, Folder 1068)
      Autograph manuscript article, signed; published in the Scots Observer, July 6, 1889. Tipped on cardboard leaves and bound in green morocco with a typescript of the article.
    - "The Freedom of Edinburgh to Follow?", 1889 July 13 (Box 51, Folder 1069)
      Autograph manuscript, signed, written for the Scots Observer, with a typed transcription bound in; bound by Sangorski & Sutcliffe.
    - "From the One to the Other One", 1893 (Box 51, Folder 1070)
      Autograph poem written to Arthur Conan Doyle after the first-night failure of Jane Annie, the opera co-written by Barrie and Doyle.
    - "Good Girl", 1893 (Box 52, Folder 1071)
      Autograph manuscript of two stanzas from a Jane Annie opera written in collaboration with Arthur Conan Doyle.
    - The Greenwood Hat, being a memoir of James Anon, 1885-1887
      A collection of autobiographical sketches, essays, and articles privately printed in Edinburgh by T. and A. Constable Ltd. in 1930; in 1937 it was reset and published by Peter Davies in London.
      - Autograph notes, [1930] (Box 52, Folder 1072)
        Contains a list of articles by Barrie with place and date of publication. Accompanied by one leaf of autograph notes.
      - Autograph manuscript, signed, [1930] (Box 52, Folder 1073)
        This manuscript includes only the introduction, envoi, and the commentary for the articles which make up the text of the book.
    - "Happy Endings", undated (Box 52, Folder 1074)
    - "Has the Author of 'He' Read 'She'?", [1887] (Box 52, Folder 1075)
      Autograph manuscript, signed. In this article Thomas Moore is assumed to be the author of "He," which was actually written by Andrew Lang and Walter Herries Pollock.
    - "Heresy Hunting", [1885-1887] (Box 52, Folder 1076)
      Autograph manuscript, signed.
    - "A Home for Geniuses", [1888] (Box 52, Folder 1077)
      Autograph manuscript, signed, which was published in Correspondence, St James's Gazette, April 19, 1888.
    - "How to be Happy Though Humorous (A Guide to Literary Beginners)", [1887] (Box 52, Folder 1078)
    - "In Disgrace", undated (Box 52, Folder 1079)
      Autograph manuscript story written in the "Auld Licht" manner. This manuscript is written in Barrie's left hand (after 1920). The story may have been composed at an earlier date and copied later by Barrie.
    - "In the Editor's Absence", 1891 (Box 52, Folder 1080)
      Autograph manuscript of an article published in the National Observer, January 31, 1891. Bound in brown morocco.
    - "International Press Cuttings Unlimited Supplied to Nicholas Llewelyn Davies, Esq.", 1926 February (Box 52, Folder 1081)
      Autograph manuscript of fictitious news clippings relating to the engagement of Nicholas Davies to Mary James (daughter of Lord Northbourne).
    - "An Invitation to Dinner", undated (Box 52, Folder 1082)
      Autograph manuscript story in letter form, written in Barrie's left hand (after 1920). The story may have been written at an earlier date and copied later by Barrie.
    - "Is it a Man?", [1890-1891] (Box 52, Folder 1083)
      Autograph manuscript, signed, of a short story published in Black and White, a Weekly Illustrated Record and Review, London, July 25, 1891. Tipped on heavy paper and bound in green morocco.
    - "Jonahs", [1886] (Box 52, Folder 1084)
    - "The Kaiser and his Dentist", [1918] (Box 52, Folder 1085)
      Autograph manuscript of an article published in the [London?] Daily Mail, September 18, 1918. This article is a parody on a series of articles by Arthur N. Davis published by the Times, August 20-September 17, 1918, titled "The Kaiser as I Know Him." Accompanied by the printed article.
    - "Lady Precious Stream", [1935] (Box 52, Folder 1086)
      Autograph manuscript evaluation of an old Chinese play, Wang Paoch'uan, as it was done into English according to its traditional style by S. I. Hsuing, London.
    - "A Lady's Shoe", circa 1893 (Box 52, Folder 1087)
      Autograph manuscript, corrected.
    - "Left-handers", 1933 (Box 52, Folder 1088)
      Autograph manuscript, signed, of an article sent to John Buchan for The Etonian, with two autograph letters, signed, to Buchan dated December 11, 1932, and March 9, 1933. Bound in red half morocco.
    - "Letter to an Eminent Author. To Mr. Andrew Lang", [1885-1886] (Box 52, Folder 1089)
      Autograph manuscript article signed.
    - "Literary Gents", undated (Box 52, Folder 1090)
      Autograph manuscript, incomplete, of an article, signed.
    - Margaret Ogilvy, 1896 July 11 (Box 52, Folder 1091)
      Autograph manuscript, signed and dated, of a biography of Barrie's mother published in New York by Scribner's (November 1896), and in London by Hodder and Stoughton (December 1896).
    - "Mark Tapley M.P.", circa 1886 (Box 52, Folder 1092)
      Autograph manuscript article, signed. This manuscript bears the London address used by Barrie from 1885-1887; an article titled "Mark Tapley" was published in the Nottingham Journal, June 9 and 13, 1884. A longer version of this article can be found in Notebook 1, page 34 (verso).
    - "Michael. A Poem", 1906 January 7 (Box 52, Folder 1093)
      Autograph manuscript of a poem written for Michael Llewelyn Davies, initialed "JMB."
    - "Mr. Baring-Gould's Novels", [1890] (Box 52, Folder 1094)
      Autograph manuscript, signed, of an article published in The Contemporary Review, February 1890.
    - "Mr. Barrie in the Chair", 1894 January 25 (Box 53, Folder 1095)
      Autograph manuscript of an article written after Barrie had presided at a public dinner in Greenock. Published in the National Observer, February 3, 1894. Tipped on cardboard leaves and bound in green morocco with a typescript of the article.
    - "Mr. George Meredith's Novels", [1888] (Box 53, Folder 1096)
      Autograph manuscript review, signed. Leaves 16 and part of 16a are missing. Bound in morocco; with the manuscript are the page proofs of the text as published in The Contemporary Review, October 1888.
    - "Mr. George Meredith's Novels", 1888–1914 (Box 53, Folder 1097)
      Printed version, bound with Barrie's "The Lost Works of George Meredith" (published in the Scots Observer, November 24, 1888), his review of Meredith's Chloe and Other Tales (published in The Paper-Knife, undated), and "Neither Dorking nor the Abbey (published in the Westminster Gazette, May 26, 1909). Also bound in: a letter from Barrie to H. Buxton Forman dated April 21, 1902. Laid in: clipping from the Glasgow News, April 23, 1914.
      Purchased from R. H. Bishop on the Frank Altschul Fund, 1953.
    - "Mr. Robey, Auctioneer", 1918 (Box 53, Folder 1098)
      Autograph manuscript of a "word-picture" written on the occasion of George Robey's concert at the Coliseum in aid of the Manor House Orthopaedic Hospital, Hampstead, May 5, 1918.
    - "Mrs. Lupraik" or "Mrs. Lapraik", [1916-1920] (Box 53, Folder 1099)
      Two autograph manuscripts of a short story (one without a title), accompanied by thirty-two pages of autograph notes for stories and plays about an actress who loses her individuality as a result of playing roles.
    - "My Husband's Play", [1915] (Box 53, Folder 1100)
      Autograph manuscript of a short story published as Chapter XXI in The Greenwood Hat. A variation of this story is published as "The New Dramatist" in The Queen's Gift Book (London: Hodder and Stoughton, 1915).
    - "Neil and Tintinnabulum"
      - Autograph manuscript, [1925] (Box 53, Folder 1101)
        Accompanied by seven leaves (some written on both sides) of autograph manuscript notes and text of different versions of the story.
      - Typescript, with autograph revisions, 1925 February 21 (Box 53, Folder 1102)
        The first leaf is missing. In gray paper wrappers.
      - Galley proof sheets with autograph revisions, 1925 May 12 (Box 54, Folder 1117)
        Published in The Flying Carpet, designed by Cynthia Asquith (London: Partridge & Co., Ltd., 1925).
      - Autograph notes for a sequel, [1925-1926] (Box 53, Folder 1103)
    - "A Note on Thomas Carlyle", [1933] (Box 53, Folder 1104)
      Autograph manuscript of an article published in the University of Edinburgh Journal 6, 1933-1934. Accompanied by one leaf of autograph notes and a typed copy of the article.
    - "Old Hyphen", undated (Box 53, Folder 1105)
      Autograph manuscript written in Barrie's left hand (after 1920); varies from the text published in MacMillan's Annual, edited by E. V. Lucas (New York, 1914), and from Chapter VII of The Greenwood Hat.
    - "On Literary Mothers. The £5 Look. (From a Correspondent)", undated (Box 53, Folder 1106)
      Autograph manuscript of an article written in Barrie's left hand (after 1920).
    - On Princesses Elizabeth and Margaret Rose, undated (Box 53, Folder 1107)
      Autograph manuscript account of Barrie's association with the royal princesses Elizabeth and Margaret.
    - "The Polite Letter-Writers at Lord's", 1922 July 15 (Box 53, Folder 1108)
      Autograph manuscript article of an exchange of fictitious letters between the members of the cricket teams of Eton and Harrow during their 93rd match at Lord's. Published anonymously as "The Polite Letter Writers" in the Eton College Chronicle, July 20, 1922. Bound in green morocco by Sangorski & Sutcliffe.
    - "The Politeness of Mr. Gosse", undated (Box 53, Folder 1109)
    - "The Private Private Secretary", undated (Box 53, Folder 1110)
      Autograph manuscript with autograph cover letter on stationery of The Grand Hotel, Sheringham, from "C. Greene" to Gordon Robbins. Accompanied by an envelope inscribed in unknown hand: "MS of Barries' anonymous article to Times ."
    - "Pro Bono Publico", [1890] (Box 53, Folder 1111)
      Autograph manuscript, signed, of an article published in the Fortnightly Review, September 1890.
    - "The Quiet Time (A Pencil Letter to his Mother Found on a 2nd Lieutenant)", [1918] (Box 53, Folder 1112)
      Autograph manuscript. The ideas expressed in this letter are also found in a letter to Elizabeth Lucas, dated February 20, 1918, and published in Letters of J. M. Barrie, edited by Viola Meynell (New York, 1947).
    - "Roosevelt", [1914] (Box 53, Folder 1113)
      Autograph notes describing a visit with and impressions of Theodore Roosevelt.
    - "Sandford and Merton", undated (Box 53, Folder 1114)
      Autograph manuscript of an article written in Barrie's left hand (after 1920); varies from the text of part (a) published in the Scots Observer, May 31, 1890. Parts (a) and (b) are published in The Greenwood Hat. This article is a parody on Thomas Day's The History of Sandford and Merton.
    - "The Satirical Rector of Diss", [1882] (Box 53, Folder 1115)
      Autograph manuscript of an article about John Skelton. Signed twice, with Nottingham and early London addresses.
    - "A School Revisited", 1895 (Box 55, Folder 1125)
      Autograph manuscript, signed, of an article published in The Youth's Companion, Boston, July 18 and August 1, 1895. Bound in full red morocco.
    - "Shakespeare-on-Avon", circa 1886 (Box 55, Folder 1126)
      Autograph manuscript, signed, of an article comparing a Shakespeare anniversary with a Burns' Day celebration.
    - "Short Cuts"
      - Autograph manuscript, signed, [1890] (Box 55, Folder 1127)
        A review of the magazine Short Cuts which was published in London from March 22 to August 20, 1890.
      - Transcription, [1890] (Box 55, Folder 1128)
        Typescript and two carbon copies.
    - "Shutting a Map", [1889] (Box 55, Folder 1129)
      One leaf of autograph manuscript of an article accompanied by six printed pages with autograph revisions. Published in the Edinburgh Evening Dispatch, September 11, 1889. The six printed pages are from The Tillyloss Scandal (New York: Lovell, Coryell and Company, 1893). It was also published in An Auld Licht Manse and Other Stories (New York: John Knox, 1893).
    - "Sleighing in England", [1886] (Box 55, Folder 1130)
    - "A Successful Journalist", undated (Box 55, Folder 1131)
    - "A Supper at the Saba", circa 1925 (Box 55, Folder 1132)
      Autograph manuscript of an article written in Barrie's left hand (after 1920). It varies from the text of "The Grandest Scene in History (by a veteran smoker)" published in St James's Gazette, April 2, 1889. William Shakespeare is the subject of the article.
    - "A Talk with the Dead", undated (Box 55, Folder 1133)
      Autograph manuscript, signed
    - "A Team for the Times. The XI Most Delightful Men in England", 1919 July (Box 55, Folder 1134)
      Autograph manuscript, signed, of an article meant for publication in the Times. Bound in blue morocco by Riviere, with a typescript explanation of the circumstances surrounding the article's creation and why it wasn't published.
    - "The Third Sex", 1891 November 11 (Box 55, Folder 1135)
      Autograph manuscript notes for stories or plays about theatrical people. A series of articles by Barrie titled "The Third Sex" were published in the Edinburgh Evening Dispatch, March 26 through June 4, 1887.
    - "Thomas Hardy. The Historian of Wessex", 1889 (Box 55, Folder 1136)
      Autograph manuscript, signed, of an article published in The Contemporary Review, July 1889. Leaves 1 and 2 are missing.
    - "Thomas Hardy O.M.", circa 1930 (Box 55, Folder 1137)
      One leaf of autograph manuscript for an article or a speech about Thomas Hardy.
    - "A Tillyloss Scandal", 1889 (Box 54, Folder 1118-1120)
      Galley proof sets, with autograph corrections and additions, for the story's original publication in Good Words, January-February 1890.
    - "To a Crooked Lady on her 33rd Birthday", 1900 (Box 55, Folder 1138)
      Autograph poem written for Sylvia Llewelyn Davies.
    - "Tom Nash", undated (Box 55, Folder 1139)
      Autograph manuscript of a critical and biographical study of Thomas Nash written sometime between 1878 and 1882; leaves 45-66 wanting.
    - "A Tragedy", undated (Box 55, Folder 1140)
    - "Twenty Portly Gentlemans", undated (Box 55, Folder 1141)
      Autograph manuscript of a poem.
    - "Two of Them", 1892 (Box 55, Folder 1142)
      Autograph manuscript, signed, of a short story published in the Christmas Number of The Graphic, London, 1892. Bound in green morocco by Sangorski & Sutcliffe.
    - "The War. An Impossible White Paper", circa 1914 (Box 55, Folder 1143)
      Autograph manuscript article with signed note: "Abandoned in the middle JMB." Leaf 28 is missing. Accompanied by one leaf, numbered 29, of another version of the article; one leaf of autograph manuscript, numbered 9, of an unidentified article discussing the importance of the press in wartime; five leaves of autograph manuscript, numbered 7-11, of an unidentified article discussing the attitude of the United States in the early phases of World War I.
    - "Who Picked Sylvia's Pocket?", undated (Box 55, Folder 1144)
      Autograph manuscript, signed and corrected, of a short story published in Harper's Magazine 84 (December 1891). Bound in red morocco by MacDonald, New York; includes as a frontispiece a 1909 photogravure portrait of Barrie by Alvin Langdon Coburn. On verso of page 6, in an unknown hand: "Drawer for Dec. No."
    - "Women Who Work: Actresses", circa 1885 (Box 55, Folder 1145)
      Autograph manuscript, signed. Another copy of this article is found on page 403 of Notebook 3.
    - [World War I], circa 1914 (Box 55, Folder 1146)
      Autograph notes discussing American attitudes in the early phases of the European conflict.
    - Untitled poem, undated (Box 55, Folder 1147)
      Autograph manuscript of a poem about the future of the children who visited Barrie at Stanway.
    - Untitled story about "Roger", undated (Box 55, Folder 1148)
      Autograph manuscript; pages 1-4 only.
    - Miscellaneous notes for essays and stories; fragments; two parodies not in Barrie's hand, undated (Box 55, Folder 1149)
      Autograph manuscripts on leaves of paper, with notes and parts of stories.
- Other Papers, 1876–1977; Series III; 25.2; 22 boxes + 1 art
  The series contains a conglomeration of non-literary material. Prominent here are some of Barrie's personal and academic papers, including a diary, schoolbooks, and writings from his time at Dumfries Academy and the University of Edinburgh; of interest too is an indenture signed by Barrie, Queen Elizabeth, and Princess Margaret Rose naming the princess as a collaborator with the author on his play The Boy David. A group of photographic, artistic, and print portraits of Barrie includes iconic images by caricaturists and illustrators, and by photographers such as Lizzie Caswall Smith, Alvin Langdon Coburn, and Frederick Hollyer. A small group of images of his theatrical colleagues includes portraits of Hilda Trevelyan and William Gillette, and a large album of professional photographs of Irene Vanbrugh portrayed in roles created by Barrie and other playwrights. Also here are folders of photographs from and illustrations for stage, film, and printed productions of Barrie's works, including an unsigned, illustrated manuscript volume, presented much like a book dummy, featuring Maude Adams in The Little Minister. Prominent illustrators whose drawings and costume designs appear in the series are Arthur Rackham, William Nicholson, Charles Ricketts, Bernard Partridge, William Hatherell, and Walt Disney Productions.
  A subseries of Realia contains a bust of Barrie, his pewter inkwell, his engraved key to London's Kensington Gardens, and a pendant presented by him to his friend Elizabeth Lucas for her work at a French children's hospital during World War I. The series ends with collections of ephemera related to Barrie and his works, and writings by other authors about him or related to him.
  Series III is organized into five subseries: Personal Papers, Graphic Material, Realia, Ephemera, and Writings by Others.
  - Personal Papers
    - Diary, 1880 (Box 56, Folder 1150)
      Autograph entries made in Campbell's Victoria Diary and Almanac for 1880 (Glasgow: Duncan Campbell & Son). The diary contains entries covering January 1 through May 17, during Barrie's second year at the University of Edinburgh. The manuscript text, annotated by Denis Mackail, is published in his The Story of J.M.B.: a Biography (London: Peter Davies, 1941).
    - Academic books and writings
      - Extracts from Attic Greek, circa 1876 (Box 56, Folder 1151)
        Textbook in the "Edinburgh Academy Class-Books" series, with autograph annotations and drawings, and inscribed: "James Barrie, The Academy, Dumfries, Feb-1876." Title page and several text pages missing.
      - "Our Dramatic Club", 1878 (Box 56, Folder 1152)
        Autograph manuscript of a chapter of a story to be written in collaboration with James McMillan, a Dumfries classmate. Initialed and dated. This story is referred to in a speech given by Barrie at Dumfries Academy, June 30, 1893, and on page 17 of the manuscript "A School Revisited," in Box 55. The notebook also contains notes for a story about a minstrel (pages 51-57) and notes for an essay, "The Reliability of Consciousness" (pages 58-72, verso). Bound in green paper.
      - Livy Books XXL and XXII, edited by W. W. Capes (London: Macmillan and Co., 1878) (Box 56, Folder 1153)
        Textbook with autograph markings; inscribed on front flyleaf: "J. M. Barrie Edinburgh University Session 1878-9."
      - Greek history class notes, 1879 (Box 56, Folder 1154)
        Autograph notes, clippings, and drawings of maps related to Greek history made in bound notebook; inscribed on first leaf: "Greek History Private Work Commenced 20th/1/79."